<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bhavesh Kakwani</title><link href="https://bhave.sh/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bhave.sh/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bhave.sh/</id><updated>2021-09-14T22:10:00-04:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>The search for alien life may end inside us</title><link href="https://bhave.sh/search-alien-end-inside-us.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-14T22:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-09-14T22:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Bhavesh Kakwani</name></author><id>tag:bhave.sh,2021-09-14:/search-alien-end-inside-us.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What if there are no aliens out there? Worse yet, what if they’re right here, inside us, and we can’t even know it?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Modified version of ‘Disruption’ by Natalie Plociennik. See the original here: https://www.natalie.gallery/gallery" src="https://bhave.sh/images/disruption_inverted.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the billionaire-led space race now in full swing, we as a species are at the cusp of a new era in space exploration. Human missions to the Moon, Mars and Venus are closer and closer within reach with each passing year. Within our lifetimes, human voyages to these celestial bodies will become commonplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the recent history of human voyages into unknown lands, we see that whenever their ships sailed, there were scientists on board. With the science they conducted, we attained a broader understanding of the geography, astronomy and botany of these newly charted lands. We traversed vast oceans - the &lt;em&gt;deep blue&lt;/em&gt; - and were rewarded with the discovery of new lifeforms and ecosystems. And now, the thirst for exploration is leading us to traverse the vast cosmic ocean of outer space - the &lt;em&gt;deep black&lt;/em&gt; - in search of new lands and, perhaps, new life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a profound question that keeps me up at night:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Are we alone in the universe?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question doesn’t have an answer, but it’s not for lack of trying. We’ve built telescopes that can sense any signal in the electromagnetic spectrum, from chonky radio waves all the way up to energetic gamma rays. We have the SETI (search for extraterrestrial life) project, which expends unfathomable computational power toward the goal of finding intelligent life out there in the &lt;em&gt;deep black&lt;/em&gt;. And now we’ve dipped our toes into even more novel forms of measuring reality, like gravitational wave detectors and giant neutrino observatories. We’ve built so many ways to see, yet all our eyes have found &lt;strong&gt;no one&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if there are no aliens out there? Worse yet, &lt;strong&gt;what if they’re right here, and we can’t even know it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about it: your body contains more bacterial cells than it does mammalian cells, and for most of history we had absolutely no idea! The soil in the world’s forests is brimming with underground mycelial networks that exchange nutrients between the plants and trees, and we didn’t even know about these fungi’s crucial role in the ecosystem &lt;strong&gt;till 1997! And let’s not even get started talking about all that’s yet to be found in the deep blue ocean.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all to say that’s it’s &lt;em&gt;really hard&lt;/em&gt; to detect other lifeforms, even when they’re right under — or inside! — our noses. To add insult to injury, all the lifeforms I mentioned above are fellow Earthlings. What hope do we have of detecting extraterrestrials?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using our narrow perspective on the universe, we are only able to imagine life that resembles what we see around us — animals, plants, bacteria and fungi. Yet it is unlikely that aliens would have a similar biology to ours. They might be built with different building blocks than cells and DNA. They might even be forged from Silicon or some other foundational element than the Carbon we’re built from. But the thought that fascinates me the most is: they might be constructed from &lt;strong&gt;entirely different kinds of fundamental particles&lt;/strong&gt; than we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Image by Kamioka Observatory, ICRR (Institute for Cosmic Ray Research), The University of Tokyo" src="https://bhave.sh/images/super_kamiokande.jpg"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image by Kamioka Observatory, ICRR (Institute for Cosmic Ray Research), The University of Tokyo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standard model of fundamental particles (we’ll get back to aliens soon, I promise), there are 17 types of particles, of which 3 are &lt;em&gt;neutrinos&lt;/em&gt;. What are neutrinos, you ask? I think Wikipedia explains it best:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The neutrino is so named because it is electrically neutral and because its rest mass is so small that it was long thought to be zero. The weak force has a very short range, the gravitational interaction is extremely weak, and neutrinos do not participate in the strong interaction. Thus, &lt;strong&gt;neutrinos typically pass through normal matter unimpeded and undetected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neutrinos are notoriously hard to detect. &lt;strong&gt;100 trillion&lt;/strong&gt; of them pass through our bodies every second, and yet virtually none of them will interact or collide with the particles you are made of. In our everyday experience, they might as well not exist. So how is it that we know about them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see that Alex Grey-/Van Gogh-esque image just above? It’s not a painting; it’s a photo of the Super-Kamiokande detector deep underground in a zinc mine in Japan. Its main purpose is to use its &lt;strong&gt;13,000 blue-light sensors&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;50,000 tons&lt;/strong&gt; of water to detect neutrinos. With a mad-science setup like that, you’d think that it detects a large number of neutrinos all the time (remember: there’s 100 trillion of them passing through your body each second). The truth is that it detected a paltry ~25 per day…an impressive feat, but it goes to show just how elusive neutrinos are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What if aliens are made of neutrinos?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;We wouldn’t be able to detect their world, but would they be able to peek into ours?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With our current technology, trying to understand the alien neutrino world would be like trying to reconstruct the earth from a bucket of air. On the other side, if the aliens have more advanced technology and can detect 'ordinary' matter, they could be watching us. I hope they think we’re cool! (Probably not). The other possibility is that they’re as clueless about us as we are about them, and they may ignorantly think the whole universe is made of neutrinos, just like our view of the cosmos is biased by our atom-tinted glasses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;They would be everywhere.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Modified version of ‘Disruption’ by Natalie Plociennik. See the original here: https://www.natalie.gallery/gallery" src="https://bhave.sh/images/disruption_inverted.png"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modified version of ‘Disruption’ by Natalie Plociennik. See the original here: &lt;a href="https://www.natalie.gallery/gallery"&gt;https://www.natalie.gallery/gallery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The neutrino-aliens would be here, there, everywhere - undetectable  - inside us, in the ocean, in volcanoes, in the clouds and in your bowl of spicy noodles. If there are trillions of these particles passing through us all the time, their entire world exists in a kind of parallel reality with ours, simultaneously taking up the same space while not interfering with each other. The aliens may orbit around the sun like we do, or maybe they’d take advantage of their low mass and travel throughout the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="*Infrared photo of a supernova hidden in the galaxy Arp 148. Credits: NASA/JPL-Caltech.*" src="https://bhave.sh/images/supernova_in_arp_148.jpeg"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Infrared photo of a supernova hidden in the galaxy Arp 148. Credits: NASA/JPL-Caltech.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;They would draw resources from the sun and from supernovae.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sun is one of the major sources of neutrinos, as are stars that go 'kaboom' at the end of their life: supernovae. These provide a steady stream of neutrinos with which the aliens can construct whatever they want in their realm. Maybe they make neutrino-based galactic tunnels, or neutrino-based 'ordinary matter’ detectors to spy on us, or even neutrino-cheeseburgers. But constructing these neutrino-objects might be challenging, because neutrinos have a relatively miniscule mass and don’t interact in all 4 force fields - which brings me to my next speculation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The aliens would be ginormous. And cold.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the nano/pico scale, all of us - including animals, plants and the earth itself - are made of quarks and electrons mostly held together by the &lt;em&gt;strong nuclear force&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;electromagnetic force&lt;/em&gt;. Both these forces are very strong and that’s why our building blocks (atoms and molecules) are so tightly packed - the forces pull them very close together and create strong bonds. Since our building blocks are small, we are small too, at least on the cosmic scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neutrinos, on the other hand, only interact with &lt;em&gt;gravity&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;weak nuclear force&lt;/em&gt;. Hence, they tend to stay far apart from each other and do not create bonds. For there to be a neutrino-based lifeform that is held together by just these two weak forces, and for it to have sufficiently complex biological parts with lots of particles, it would be unfathomably large. Even the neutrino-land equivalent of a single-celled bacteria would be orders of magnitude larger than any human being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The neutrino-alien would also have to be &lt;strong&gt;cold&lt;/strong&gt;. If it was warm, the neutrinos would zip around much faster (that’s what “warmth" is) and the weak forces would not be able to hold all the neutrinos together. It would shred apart into nothingness. But if it was a cold creature — near absolute zero temperature - its neutrinos would be moving slow enough to be “captured" and held together by the weak forces and its life would be way more chill (sorry).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To these giant, freezing aliens, we could seem as insignificant in size as a virus is to us. So maybe the aliens are not inside us, but &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; are inside &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Our perception of the cosmos is a narrow slit in the dark void.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We humans, as a quarter-million-year-old species, have only just come to realize our ignorance of nature in the last few centuries. In that short time, we have made tremendous strides forward in our understanding of our planet and the universe, from gravity to quantum mechanics. But if there’s one thing we’re sure of, it’s that we’ve hardly scratched the surface of all there is to learn and discover. I have hope that our rapid pace of scientific discovery will lead us to find new realms and parallel worlds…and maybe, just maybe, to discover alien life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acknowledgments: this piece was probably subconsciously inspired by one of my favourite books - Three Body Problem by Cixin Liu - which describes in detail a very interesting alien lifeform and the advanced civilization and culture they build. I would also like to thank these wonderful humans for reviewing my draft and giving me feedback: Nabeela Merchant, Jeff Emmanuel, Danielle Griscti and Natalie Plociennik.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;P.S. if you have a physics background and this made you cringe multiple times due to inaccuracies, please chat with me about it! I’d love to hear your rants so I can better understand the subject and maybe write a ‘harder’ sci-fi piece next time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;P.P.S. if you think this thought experiment is whacky and highly improbable, you are probably right! I invite you to imagine what kind of worlds and creatures may exist if they were made of different particles or micro-structures than we are. There’s probably a better building block than neutrinos for making intelligent life out of.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Articles"></category><category term="aliens"></category><category term="space"></category><category term="neutrinos"></category><category term="thought experiment"></category></entry><entry><title>How to align a team towards better code quality</title><link href="https://bhave.sh/align-team-code-quality.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-08T09:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-09-08T09:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Bhavesh Kakwani</name></author><id>tag:bhave.sh,2021-09-08:/align-team-code-quality.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two major things that erode code quality in a company are code duplication and non-standard coding style. How do you tackle these issues?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A lily of the valley plant in High Park, Toronto" src="https://bhave.sh/images/lily_of_the_valley.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two major issues that erode code quality in a company are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;code duplication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;non-standard coding style.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tackle these, I held meetings with my team to identify common functionalities that everyone expects (and often repeatedly re-implements) in their software modules. From these meetings, I gathered all these common functionalities as well as additional feature requests and made them the requirements for a new library I would implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The library I architected handled foundational aspects of flight software modules such as message passing between modules, tracking state in state machines, a common command interface to allow manipulation of the state machine, sensible diagnostic log messages, and an 'error' state to allow for root cause analysis of a software module's failure. The library does a great job of enacting the DRY (don't repeat yourself) principle. Each new software module to be written would be an object that inherits from this library's main class, and thus benefits from all the features without having to implement them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By creating this and explaining to the team the philosophy behind the library and how to best use it, I was able to create a coding culture/style that is consistent among all developers on our team. The mundane parts of the code became more robust and predictable, and this helped to prevent a lot of software bugs and errors. The team got engaged as stakeholders and helped me by further refining the library and adding needed features, without causing too much code-bloat/scope-creep. Code reviews became much easier too, because now we all write code in a similar way so we are familiar with the structure and can focus on the unique details of each implementation. Finally, the code is now completely modular as there are well-defined interfaces between modules, the controller and the receivers (GUIs). All of these contributed to a codebase that is of much higher quality than before.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Articles"></category><category term="software"></category><category term="teamwork"></category><category term="DRY"></category></entry><entry><title>Habits &amp; life-hacks from the sleep community</title><link href="https://bhave.sh/habits-life-hacks-sleep-community.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-24T17:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-24T17:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Bhavesh Kakwani</name></author><id>tag:bhave.sh,2021-08-24:/habits-life-hacks-sleep-community.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What technologies/methods do you use to help you sleep at night? What do you wish was better?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Me sleeping on my friend on a couch" src="https://bhave.sh/images/me_sleeping.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apparently, I use my friends to help me sleep&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached out to people in sleep communities on facebook and reddit, and asked a couple of open-ended questions: &lt;strong&gt;What technologies/methods do you use to help you sleep at night? What do you wish was better?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responses were varied and amazing! I’m copying them below for your viewing pleasure, followed by my &lt;strong&gt;analysis at the end:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headspace has changed my life so much. I have had anxiety disorder my entire life. I couldn’t sit through a movie. Had to be moving. Headspace has changed that. I can now fall asleep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I keep a calming aroma-pillow spray.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plants have completely changed my home. It feels relaxing, productive, and reminds me to both meditate, exercise and keep a good sleep schedule. So I would recommend plants in the home and the bedroom. I also recommend a strict sleep schedule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An eyemask for sure! I need it pure dark to sleep so that helps so much. I also have a lamp that I set to fade over 30–45 minutes so that I don’t stay up super late reading. It’s also a wakeup light (starts getting brighter over 30 minutes), which is nice and makes bird sounds which is peaceful to wake to. And I use a bluetooth headband to listen to the [Sleep With Me] podcast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use this eye mask / headphone combo and I love it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wish I could make a play list of [Sleep With Me podcast] episodes I like and listen to it on my Alexa.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I started listening to the [Sleep With Me] podcast to get away from falling asleep to TV. I like to play this game (two dots) as I’m winding down and starting the podcast. i know screens aren’t great before bed but it calms my mind down and keeps me from scrolling on social media!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I play a good old bubble popping game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wish that there were sleep phones with softer speakers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lavender linen spray. Dark room. Cold room. Meditative breathing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three pairs generic wired sleep phones went to the big farm. Also, I did not like the sound on the bluetooth. I bought these MMUSS replacement wired phones to put in my head bands.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I fall asleep instantly to these Headspace sleepcasts. (They are more visual than the [Sleep With Me] podcast.) Then later I put on an all night Sleep With Me episode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fan and a white noise machine in addition to a few hours of Scoots [/Sleep With Me podcast].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tried a huge array of [sleep] masks including smart ones and fabric ones with specific eye cushions for $30+. Honestly, what has worked for me the best is a simple molded eye cup mask with nothing fancy. The molded eyecups are so that no fabric is touching your eyes/eyelashes as you’re trying to fall asleep. It is the most basic one($4.99) and it has been the most effective. I have one by my bed, in the car(as a passenger), and in my travel kit when I’m on planes and at the airport.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very interesting responses! Let’s break them down into some categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Problems people deal with:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxiety and/or inability to calm the mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inability to stick to regular sleep schedule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bedroom not dark enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The draw of social media scrolling at night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jetlag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Solutions &amp;amp; hacks people employ:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Audio:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcasts &amp;amp; “sleepcasts” (Sleep With Me or Headspace).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleep mask with Bluetooth/wired “soft” headphones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White noise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Light:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timer/smart lamps that fade out at night and up in the morning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well fitted sleep mask / dark room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Smell:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pillow / linen spray (lavender, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. Activity:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calming smartphone games (bubble popping, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breathing exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there is definitely a market here. In any case, I could certainly personally use a solution that helps keep me keep a strong sleep schedule and feel refreshed everyday, given my busy life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing I noticed is that almost all the respondents were middle-aged women! Perhaps this is a sampling bias because most of them were from facebook, but I’ll keep a lookout to see if this pattern continues in my future research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Articles"></category><category term="sleep"></category></entry></feed>